In this lecture, we will cover floating point numbers.
First, we'll learn about how floating point numbers are represented in binary.
Then we'll look at how to perform arithmetic with them.
To start, we motivate why we need a floating point representation in the first place.
In many applications, we want to be able to represent a large range of numbers without needing much precision.
For example, if we wanted to represent numbers ranging from 3 to 1,572,864 in a typical integer or fixed point encoding,
we would need at least 21 bits.
The value 3 is all leading zeros followed by 1,1, while the value 1,572,864 is 1,1, followed by all trailing zeros.
But these running zeros are a waste of space in the binary encoding.
The value 3 is just 1.1 times 2 to the first, while the big number is just 1.1 times 2 to the 20th.
So for both numbers, we really only need two bits of information and an exponent value.
The exponent effectively tells us where the point is.
For 3, the point is in bit position 1, while for the large number, the point is in bit position 20.
This notation is referred to as floating point.
Notice how it's very similar to the scientific notation that we use for very large or very small decimal numbers.
The floating point format consists of three binary fields, a sign bit, an exponent field, and the fraction field.
Looking at the value formula, you can see that if the sign bit is 1, then the encoded value is negative.
The exponent bits specify at which bit position the point is located.
And the fraction bits specify the actual number that's encoded minus the implicit leading 1.
Here, we're showing an example floating point representation that uses a 4-bit exponent and a 5-bit fraction.
As shown, the decimal number 9.25 can be represented as 1.00101 times 2 to the third in binary.
Thus, the exponent value is 3 and the fraction is 00101.
There are two things to note.
First, the significant is generally normalized such that there is an implicit or hidden leading 1 in front of the point.
With that, the leading 1 doesn't have to be encoded and we can use that bit for exponent or fraction.
The second thing is that the exponent is often stored in biased form.
We will discuss this more in the coming slides.
The IEEE 754 standard defines two precision levels for floating point numbers.
In single 32-bit precision, the exponent is 8 bits and the fraction is 23 bits.
Single precision floats can represent numbers roughly as high as 2 to the 127th and as low as 2 to the negative 126th.
In double or 64-bit precision, the exponent is 11 bits and the significant is 52 bits.
It can represent a broader range of numbers.
Why is the significant normalized?
Without normalization, we end up with multiple ways of representing the same number.
For example, the decimal number 9.25 can be represented as 1001.01 times 2 to the 0 or 100.101 times 2 to the 1st and so on.
So the standard encoding is to normalize this significant such that we only have one leading bit in front of the binary point.
Since every number has this leading 1, this bit becomes implicit and is not encoded, leaving just the fraction field.
Now this way, every number has a unique representation.
In floating point numbers, the exponent can either be positive or negative.
The latter is used to represent small numbers that are close to zero.
As mentioned briefly earlier, it is generally preferred to encode the exponent in a biased or excess notation instead of in two's complement.
The reason for this is to simplify sorting.
It's much easier to sort numbers if a larger exponent value implies a larger floating point value.
Floating point numbers with negative exponents are smaller in value than numbers with positive exponents.
However, when viewed as unsigned values, negative exponents seem bigger since their most significant bits are one.
So instead, exponents are generally encoded based on a predefined bias value.
Revisiting our example from earlier, we can use a biased notation for the exponent where the predefined bias is seven.
So now if we wish to represent two to the third, for example, we actually set E to be ten instead of three since ten minus seven equals three.
IEEE 754 uses a bias of 127 for single precision floating point and a bias of 1,023 for double precision.
This table shows examples how exponent values are encoded in single precision.
Notice how with two's complement exponents, it becomes difficult to sort values.
You would have to do a signed comparison of the exponent and then perform an unsigned comparison of the six significance just to compare two floating point numbers.
On the other hand, by using a bias, larger exponent values always have a larger unsigned encoding as shown in the rightmost column.
Thus comparing two floating point numbers becomes as simple as unsigned integer comparison.
Note that the IEEE floating point standard also supports special cases shown here.
First, the value zero is simply encoded as all zeros in both single and double precision.
For numbers that are very small and close to zero, we don't actually normalize the significant anymore.
These cases are specified by an exponent value of zero, which is the smallest exponent supported.
Conversely, infinity can be encoded by setting the maximum exponent and setting the significant bits to zero.
And lastly, undefined values, or not a number, are encoded by setting the max exponent with a non-zero significant.
Note that denormalized numbers allow for gradualized underflow. You get smaller numbers and you do not quite underflow quite as quickly.
Here's a website where you can look at setting your own values.
Next, we'll discuss floating point overflow and underflow.
Floating point overflow is analogous to integer overflow in that the result is too large to be represented.
This is detected when the exponent is too big.
Floating point underflow is the reverse when the result is too small or too negative.
Both of these scenarios can trigger an exception under the IEEE standard, if enabled.
Now we'll move on to how to perform addition on floating point numbers.
It turns out that this is just like adding decimal numbers in scientific notation, as shown in the example here.
Given two numbers, first thing you have to do is align their points on top of each other by shifting the smaller number.
Then from there, we can directly add the significant values as in regular integer addition.
And then finally, we normalize the sum so that there's only one digit in front of the decimal point and then round the final sum.
Now we'll apply this process to the binary floating point representation from earlier.
Now we're adding two values, 1.11001 times 2 to the third and 1.1001 times 2 to the first.
For reference, the exponents are shown here in biased form as well.
So first thing we do is shift the second operand to the right since it's smaller so that we can align the points.
Now that both are normalized to 2 to the third, we can directly add them using integer arithmetic.
After adding, we find that the sum has two leading bits so we need to perform normalization.
Thus, we shift the sum to the right by one, which consequently increases the exponent by one.
Then finally, since the significant needs to be six bits only, we round the value and drop the least significant bits.
This slide illustrates the typical hardware organization of a floating point adder.
From top to bottom, first we need to compare the exponents of the incoming operands using a small ALU
so that we can identify the smaller operand and shift its significant to line up the points.
Then we need a bigger ALU to add the aligned significance.
Then, depending on the resulting sum, we need to shift the significant left or right to normalize it,
which consequently increments or decrements the exponent value.
Then finally, we round the sum.
Let's dig a little deeper into rounding.
Turns out, rounding is surprisingly very important because with the billions of operations that a typical program performs,
small rounding errors can really accumulate and have a major impact on the program's result.
Let's go through the previous example once again, except now, we'll account for the fact that our hardware would only have a six-bit adder since the significant is only six bits.
Because of this, some least significant bits are dropped during the sum computation.
Then, with normalization, we may end up dropping even more bits.
And because all of these lost bits, we're unable to make an accurate decision of whether to round up or round down.
To support rounding for addition, the FP adder actually needs to introduce a guard bit.
The guard bit is effectively just an extra bit that we append to the right of the significant.
This allows us to retain an extra bit of precision in the values, and thus we can use a seven-bit adder.
Now, even after normalization, the guard bit is able to retain an extra bit, which happens to be one in this case.
Now with this, we're able to make a better decision to either round up or round down appropriately.
Now we'll move on to floating point multiplication.
To perform multiplication, we need to do a few things.
First, we need to compute the signed bit of the product.
This is simply a matter of XORing the signed bits of the operands.
Second, we need to compute the product's exponent.
To do this, we add the biased exponent values of the operands.
Since the two input exponent values are already biased, the sum will be doubly biased, so we need to subtract the bias once.
Then, to compute the product's significant, we simply perform standard integer multiplication on the significant as they are.
Note that no shifting nor alignment needs to be performed before multiplying them.
Then, after this, we may need to re-normalize and round, just like in addition, where we shift the significant in increment or decrement exponent accordingly.
Here we outline the specific steps that need to be taken.
First, we compute the sign, exponent, and significance of the product, as just discussed.
Then we perform normalization incrementally.
Depending on the current significant value, we shift left or right once.
Then we check for overflow or underflow and round the significant.
Then, we check again, and if it's still not normalized, go back to step two.
Here we show an example of floating point multiplication.
We'll assume we have a guard bit for rounding, as introduced earlier.
Let's start with computing the exponent.
We need to add A's biased exponent, which is 10, with B's biased exponent, which is 8.
This gives us 18, but then we need to subtract the bias of 7, so the product's biased exponent value is 11, which represents 2 to the 4th.
Now let's compute the significant hand by simply performing fixed point multiplication on A and B's significant hands.
Note that this yields a 6-bit product with an extra guard bit.
Now, we normalize by shifting the significant right by 1 bit and incrementing the exponent.
And then finally, using the guard bit, we round the final 6-bit product.
Let's look at another example with different values for A and B.
As before, we compute the product's exponent and significant hand values.
But this time, note that the leading bit of the significant hand is 0 after multiplying the input's significant hands.
As a result, after we normalize, we're actually left with a guard bit as among the 6-bits of the significant hand.
As a result, when we get to rounding, we don't have any bits left beyond the guard bit, and this leads to a potential rounding error.
So with this, let's revisit floating point rounding hardware.
Modern implementations usually introduce two more bits in addition to the guard bit.
The first is a round bit, which just serves as an extra guard bit for floating point multiplication.
As shown in the previous example, sometimes multiplying the significant hands results in a leading 0-bit.
This leads to the guard bit getting shifted into the significant hand itself.
So the round bit allows us to retain an additional bit for rounding in this particular case.
The second additional bit is the sticky bit, which effectively serves as the final guard bit.
During the multiplication and normalization, several bits may get shifted out and dropped.
The sticky bit gets set to 1 if any of those drop bits are 1, so it's effectively a logical oar of all of these bits.
This allows us to remember if there were any 1 bits that we dropped in order to help us decide when appropriate to round up.
Now with this, let's redo the previous example.
This time, when we compute the product's significant hand, we retain not only a guard bit, but also a round bit and a sticky bit,
where the sticky bit is the logical oar of all the other bits that were dropped.
As before, the guard bit ends up in the 6-bit significant hand, but now that we've retained additional bits,
we have more information to accurately round the final product.
To close out this lecture, let's go through another example of multiplication with 3 rounding bits.
Given the inputs A and B, as shown, show the significant and exponent of the product at each step of the multiplication.
Please pause the video and try to go through the answer.
This is actually the same example from a few slides ago, except now you have to account for the round bit and sticky bit.
As a result, we're able to retain a 6-bit significant hand along with a guard bit and a round bit and a sticky bit,
which is equal to 1, which is the logical oar of the 4 bits that were dropped.
Then with this, we're able to normalize and round the final product appropriately.